Guide to the Atwater Family Papers, 1788 - 2003
Atwater Family Papers, 1788 - 2003
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
2008-36
17.6 41
Four generations of Atwaters and their spouses are represented in the family papers: William Warren Atwater (1814-1874), Wilbur Olin Atwater (1844-1907), Helen Woodard Atwater (1876-1947), Charles Woodard Atwater (1885-1946), Catherine Merriam Atwater (1913-2008), Charles Woodard Atwater, Jr. (1920-2002). The Atwaters are associated mostly with Middletown, Connecticut and Plandrom, New York. The papers contain correspondence, photographs, financial and estate papers, research and student notes, and other materials. The papers include family correspondence about family and home matters, travel and visitors; college and social life; and career and professional activities. Wilbur Olin Atwater's letters describe his work and travels in Washington, D.C., Europe, Russia, and Cuba. Helen Atwater's materials include her household and personal finances, and letters from a colleague about war-time and post-war Holland. Some of her correspondence addresses her work in the federal Department of Home Economics. Charles' letters to Helen offer her occasional investment and banking advice. Correspondence between Catherine Atwater Galbraith and her brother Robert discuss family matters including their brother Charles' mental health, condition, and care.
Atwater Family Papers contain correspondence, photographs, financial and estate papers, research and student notes, and other materials from four generations of the family. The papers include family correspondence about family and home matters, travel and visitors, letters from college include commentary on classes, lectures, concerts, and social life, and career and professional activities. Wilbur Olin Atwater's documents include study notes and some college lab notebooks, materials from his research travels in Europe, Russia, and Cuba as well as letters describing his work and travels. His daughter Helen's materials include her household and personal finances, and letters from a colleague about war-time and post-war Holland. Some of her correspondence addresses her work in the federal Department of Home Economics. Wilbur's son Charles' letters to Helen offer her occasional investment and banking advice, noting in 1932 "it is anti-social to horde money at this stage." Correspondence between Catherine Atwater Galbraith and her brother Robert discuss family matters including their brother's mental health, condition, and care. Charles letters describe his work as a farm hand prior to college and during vacations, his service experience as Pharmacist's Mate, and his deepening interest in foreign policy immediately following his military service.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Gift of the estate of Catherine Merriam Atwater Galbraith via J. Alan Galbraith executor, in December 2008 and January 2009 (accessions 2008-35 and 2009-01).
Biographical and Historical Note
William Warren Atwater (1814-1874) was the son of Thomas Atwater and Betsy Boyden Atwater. He was a minister of the Methodist Episcopal Church and temperance advocate in New York and New England. He became librarian of Yale Law School in New Haven, Connecticut in 1872. He married Eliza Barnes and they had two children, Wilbur Olin (1844-1907) and Florence Amelia (b. May 29, 1852).
Wilbur Olin Atwater (1844-1907) was the son of William Warren Atwater. He graduated Wesleyan with the Class of 1865, and earned a Ph.D. in agricultural chemistry from Yale in 1869. He taught at the University of Tennessee, Maine State College, and then Wesleyan University from 1873 to 1907. Atwater was the director of the first American agricultural experiment station, in Middletown, CT, and was later appointed chief of the Office of Experiment Stations in Washington, D.C. (1888-1891). His work in calorimetric study was well known; he researched and published extensively in physiological chemistry and agricultural chemistry. He married Marcia Woodard in 1874. They had two children: Helen Woodard Atwater and Charles Woodard Atwater.
Marcia Woodard Atwater (1851-1932) was the daughter of Abram Woodard of Bangor, Maine, and sibling of Charles and Sarah. She married Wilbur Olin Atwater; they had two children Helen and Charles. Mrs. Atwater lived in Washington, D.C. from 1914 to 1929, and returned to Middletown, Connecticut.
Helen Woodard Atwater (1876-1947), was the daughter of Marcia Woodard Atwater and Wilbur Olin Atwater. She graduated Smith College in 1897. She became an editorial assistant to her father and in 1909 went to work for the Office of Home Economics in the Department of Agriculture as a science staff member. From 1923 to 1941 she was editor of the American Home Economics Association's The Journal of Home Economics, expanding the magazine's reach to scientific and education audiences. She was a member of the Women's Joint Congressional Committee and represented the American Home Economics Association at international conferences. She was a member of the American Association for the Advancement of Science. Helen died in Washington in 1947.
Charles Woodard Atwater (1885-1946) was the son of Wilbur Olin Atwater and Marcia Woodard Atwater. Charles attended Philips Exeter Academy, graduated Wesleyan with the Class of 1906, and went on to Harvard to earn a law degree. He moved to New York in 1910, and later established his own law firm, Atwater and Clarke. He served as Consul General for Siam (Thailand). He married Alice Caroline Merriam in 1911. They had three children: Catherine Merriam Atwater (1913-2008), Robert Merriam Atwater (b.1916), and Charles Woodard Atwater, Jr. (1920-2002).
Alice Caroline Merriam Atwater (d.1950) was the daughter of Joseph and Abbie Wilson Merriam of Middletown, Connecticut. She had two siblings, Robert and Helen. She attended Smith College from 1905 to 1907. She married Charles Atwater in October 1911. They had three children.
Catherine Merriam Atwater (1913-2008) was the daughter of Alice Caroline Merriam Atwater and Charles Woodard Atwater. She graduated Smith College with the Class of 1934 and studied at Radcliffe, earning a master's degree in 1937. She married the economist John Kenneth Galbraith in 1937. They had four sons: J. Alan, Douglas, Peter W., and James K. She was a writer.
Charles Woodard Atwater, Jr. (1920-2002) was the son of Alice Caroline Merriam Atwater and Charles Woodard Atwater. He earned a B.S. in Agronomy from Cornell University in 1942, served in the Coast Guard during World War II, experienced mental illness resulting in hospitalizations at the Veterans Administration hospitals, and lived in Tyngsboro, Massachusetts.
Collection Overview
Collection Arrangement
The Atwater Family Papers are arranged in 13 series by family member and material form.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Atwater, Charles Woodard, 1885-1946.; Atwater, Charles Woodard, Jr., 1920-2002.; Atwater family.; Atwater, Helen W.; Atwater, W. O. (Wilbur Olin), 1844-1907.; Galbraith, Catherine Atwater.; Diaries.; Home economics--United States.; Mental health.; Middletown (Conn.)--Social life and customs--19th century.; Middletown (Conn.)--Social life and customs--20th century.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Alumni and alumnae.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Social life and customs--20th century.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I. William Warren Atwater, 1788-1878, .25 linear feet
  Includes his handwritten six-page biography, and anonymous threats made in response to his work towards the "overthrow of rum traffic" in northern Vermont.
  - Methodist Episcopal Church certificates, 1840-1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1845-1873 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Vermont Directory and Commercial Almanac by W.W. Atwater, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Autobiography, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - State Appraisers' Warrant and Report, 1878 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - An Almanack, for the Year of Christian Era by Abraham Weatherwise, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II. Wilbur Olin Atwater, 1863-1989, 2.5 linear feet
  Includes his correspondence and personal papers. Atwater's letters to his future wife include commentary on his classes, lectures and concerts he attended. He records his observations of people he meets in Washington, D.C. and abroad including his introduction to Leon Trotsky (1897). The series includes letters to his children. The series also contains some personal papers from his days at Wesleyan, a diary of study notes and lab notebooks, and correspondence and other materials documenting his travels in Brussels, Germany, Switzerland, Italy, Russia, and Cuba. His letters sometimes mention plans for the Chicago World's Fair (1893) and the Bruxelles Exposition Universelle.
  - Correspondence
    - Wilbur Olin Atwater - Marcia Woodward Atwater, 1873 Jan, Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1873 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1874 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1874 Mar (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1874 Apr-May (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1874 Jun-Aug, Dec (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1875 Jan, Apr (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1875 Sep (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1875 Oct, Dec (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1875 Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1876 Jan, Apr (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1877 Aug, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1889 Feb-Jun (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1889 Jul-Aug (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1889 Sep (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1889 Oct (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1889 Nov (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1890 Jan (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1890 Feb, Apr (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1890 May-Jun (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1890 Jul (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1890 Aug-Sep (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1890 Oct-Nov (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1890 Dec (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 1891 Jan (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - 1891 Feb-Mar (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 1892 Jan-Feb (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1892 Mar (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1892 Sep-Dec (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1893 Jan-Mar (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1893 Apr (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1893 May-Aug (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1893 Sep (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1895-1896 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1897 Jun-Jul (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1897 Aug (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1897 Sep-Oct (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1900 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1903-1904, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Transcriptions of letters (Draft 1), 1889 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Transcriptions of letters (Draft 2), 1889 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Transcriptions of letters, 1890 Jan (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Transcriptions of letters, 1890 Aug-Dec (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Transcriptions of letters, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Wilbur Olin Atwater - Helen Woodard Atwater, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1892 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1893-1895 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1897 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1899 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1900 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1903 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1904 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Wilbur Olin Atwater - Charles Woodard Atwater, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 1892 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 1893 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 1894-1895 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Wilbur Olin Atwater to Charles and Helen Woodard Atwater, 1897 Jul (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Wilbur Olin Atwater to Charles Woodard Atwater, 1897-1898 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - 1900 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - 1902-1903 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Wilbur Olin Atwater - Family, 1876-1892 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Wilbur Olin Atwater - Annie, 1867 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - 1868 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - 1870 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Wilbur Olin Atwater - Others, 1866-1884 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - 1900-1905 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Personal Papers
    - Wesleyan University tuition receipts, 1863-1869 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Diary (study notes), 1864 May-Jun (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Wesleyan essays, notes, assignments, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Printed material: Wesleyan Quadrennial Anniversary of Phi Nu Theta, Junior Jubilee, clippings on chemistry, 1866 Jul, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Notebook (laboratory notes), 2 vols., 1869 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Smithsonian Institution: letter of introduction, 1891 Jul 3 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - H.R. 7921 Nutritive Economy of Food Bill, 1892 Apr 6 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Hotel Des Alpes Chamonix Menu, 1892 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Trip to Russia notes, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Tolstoy as Preacher with letter and photo by I. H. Harrison, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Arthur P. Bryant manuscript, Food, with letter, 1898 Mar 5 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Notes on trip to Cuba, 1901-1902 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Passenger list for Norddeutscher Lloyd Bremen, 1903 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Receipts, 1903 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Professor Armstrong's Report on Respiration Calorimeter, 1904 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Wilbur Olin Atwater obituary and biographical information, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Printed materials: Fifty Years of Progress in the Chemistry of Physiology and Nutrition in the United States 1876-1926 by Graham Lusk, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Dedication program for the Atwater Laboratory, 1930 Jun (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Printed materials: miscellaneous clippings, 1944, 1947, Undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Printed materials: miscellaneous clippings, 1940, 1989, Undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Printed materials: Wilbur Olin Atwater - A Biographical Sketch by L. A. Maynard; Science at Wesleyan 1831-1942 by Burton Camp, 1962, [1969] (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Photocopies of letters and draft article by R. A. Gortner, [1974?] (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Atwater Centennial Symposium, 1992-1994 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Wesleyan University Museum medals on loan, Undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Series III. Marcia Woodard Atwater, 1870-1951, 2.75 linear feet
  Contains Marcia's correspondence with her husband and children and with her father, Abram Woodard, her sister, Sarah Woodard, and brother, Charles Woodard. There is small amount of correspondence with others. She writes of family matters, her and her family's travel, visitors, and house matters. The personal papers include financial and estate documents and documents regarding the care of cousin Frederick Adams and the guardianship of Arthur Spatcher.
  - Correspondence
    - Marcia Woodard Atwater - Charles Woodard Atwater, 1895-1896 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1898-1899 Aug (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1899 Aug-Sep (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1901 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1902 Jan (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1902 Feb (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1902 Mar (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1902 May (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1903 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1904-1905 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - 1906 Jun-Jul (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 1906 Jul (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - 1906 Jul (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - 1906 Aug (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - 1906 Aug (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - 1907 Oct (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - 1907 Nov-Dec (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - 1909 Sep (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Marcia Woodard Atwater - Helen Woodard Atwater, 1897 Apr-Jun (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - 1897 Jul-Aug (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - 1897 Sep (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - 1898 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - 1899 Mar-Aug (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Marcia Woodard Atwater - Helen Woodard Atwater, 1899 Aug-Sep, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1901 May-Sep (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1903 Jan-Sep (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1903 Oct (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1903 Nov (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1904 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 1904 Dec-1905 Jan (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1905 Jan (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - 1905 Jan (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - 1907 Aug (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - 1908 Sep (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - 1913 Feb-Mar (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 1913 Mar-Apr (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - 1913 Apr-May (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Marcia Woodard Atwater - Wilbur Olin Atwater, 1873 Jan-Aug (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - 1873 Sep-Oct (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - 1873 Nov-Dec (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - 1874 Jan (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - 1874 Feb (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - 1874 Feb (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - 1874 Mar (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - 1874 Mar (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1874 Apr (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1874 May (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 1874 May (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - 1874 Jun (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 1874 Jun (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - 1874 Jul (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - 1875 Jul-Sep (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - 1875 Oct-Dec (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - 1876 Jan-Mar (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - 1876 Apr-May (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - 1876 Jun-Sep (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - 1890 Feb-Jun (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - 1890 Jul (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - 1890 Jul-Aug (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - 1890 Sep-Nov (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - 1890 Nov-Dec (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - 1891 Jan (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - 1891 Feb (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - 1891 Jun, Sep (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - 1892 Jan (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1892 Feb (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1892 Mar (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1892 Apr (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1892 May (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1892 Jun (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1892 Jul-Dec (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 1893 Jan-Feb (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - 1893 Mar (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - 1893 Apr (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - 1893 May (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - 1894 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - 1895 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - 1897 Jul-Aug (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - 1897 Sep (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - 1898 Aug-Sep (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - 1900 Jan-May (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - 1900 Sep (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - 1901 May (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - 1902 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - 1903 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Undated (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Marcia Woodard Atwater - Abram Woodard, 1874 Aug-Sep (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1874 Oct (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1874 Nov-Dec (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1875 Jan-Feb (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1875 Mar (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1875 Apr (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1875 May-Jun (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 1875 Nov, Undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - F. A. Atwater, 1895 Sep (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Charles Woodard - Marcia Woodard Atwater, 1882-1883, 1905 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Sarah Woodard - Marcia Woodard Atwater, 1883 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Henry D. Barnard, Undated, Nov 30 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Mary L. Dunn?, 1876 Sep (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Marcia Woodard Atwater - Others, 1872-1873 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - 1892-1899 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - 1900-1907 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - 1908-1910, Undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Personal Papers
    - Commonplace book (1870), Travel diary (1882), 1870, 1882 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Guardianship of Arthur Spatcher, 1900 Apr 24 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Financial papers, 1909-1929 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Bon pour L'Angleterre on pour la Registration de France, 1914 Aug 28 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Obituary, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Estate papers, 1949-1951 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Estate of Frederick W. Adams, 1926 Sep (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Estate papers: Alice Merriam Atwater, 1949-1951 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Series IV. Helen Woodard Atwater, 1885-1948, 2 linear feet
  Contains Helen's correspondence with her parents and her brother Charles. A modest amount of correspondence describes a possible move of the Home Economics department from the Department of Agriculture to the Bureau of Standards. There are some letters from "Willie" Kits van Warren describing war-time and post-war experiences in Haarlem, Holland. Also in this series is some personal correspondence, financial and estate papers including her mother's trust fund, household accounts, and tax returns.
  - Correspondence
    - Helen Woodard Atwater - Charles Woodard Atwater, 1895 Oct-Nov (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1898 Aug-Oct (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1899 Aug-Sep (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 1901 Oct-Dec (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 1902 Jan-Feb (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1905 Nov (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1906 Jul-Aug (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - 1907 Oct (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - 1907 Nov (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - 1907 Dec (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - 1909 Sep (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Helen Woodard Atwater - Charles Woodard Atwater, Jr., 1942 Apr (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Helen Woodard Atwater - Marcia Woodard Atwater, 1885 Aug (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - 1892 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - 1894 Nov-Dec (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - 1895 Jan-Mar (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - 1895 Aug-Oct (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - 1897 Mar-Jun (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - 1897 Aug-Sep (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - 1901 Apr (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - 1908 Sep (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - 19011 Feb-Apr (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 19011 Mar-May (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Helen Woodard Atwater - Wilbur Olin Atwater, 1885 Aug (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - 1890 May (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 1890 Jul (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - 1892 Jan-Jul (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - 1893 Jan-Mar (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - 1893 Apr-May (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - 1893 Sep (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - 1894 Sep-Nov (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - 1895 Jan (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - 1897 Jun-Oct (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - 1898 Aug-Sep (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - 1903 Jul (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Undated (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Helen Woodard Atwater - Family, 1894 Dec (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - 1895 Mar (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Helen Woodard Atwater - Wilbur and Marcia Atwater, 1899 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Helen Woodard Atwater - Others, 1903-1947 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Luther?, 1924-1925 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - S. Mary Ives, M.D., 1929 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Miss Cutts?, 1946 Aug (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Frances Gordon, Undated (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Financial Papers
    - Bank book - Middletown National Bank, 1917-1931 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Corp, 1923-1947 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Chemical Bank and Trust, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Farmers Loan and Trust Co., 1928 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Farmers and Mechanics Savings Bank, 1922 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Fox-Becker Granite Co., 1932-1933 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - G-H, 1923-1930 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - J-N, 1926-1933 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Receipts - Miscellaneous, 1893-1947 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Rhode Island Hospital Trusts, 1942-1947 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - S, 1919-1932 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - T, 1924-1947 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Taxes, 1933-1934 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Taxes, 1943-1948 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Taxes, 1943-1948 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Estate Papers
    - Appraisal notes, Undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Appraisment of Estate of Helen Woodard Atwater, 1947 Sep (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Chemical Bank and Trust, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Hoppin Bros. and Co., 1947-1948 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Peaslee and Turlington: estate taxes, 1947-1948 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Wills, 1932-1947 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Personal Papers
    - Typed manuscript, "Home Economics Research in the U.S. Department of Agriculture", 1904? (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Diary, 1901-1904 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Diary, 1912-1914 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Literary Club Play, 1911 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Obituary clippings, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Helen W. Atwater International Scholarship Fund Committee, [1948] (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Biographical information, Undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
- Series V. Charles Woodard Atwater, 1892-1948, 2 linear feet
  Contains correspondence between Charles and Alice before their marriage. There is also correspondence between Charles and his sister, Helen Woodard Atwater, his parents, and friends. He writes to his future wife about college life at Wesleyan University, and a "machine ride" (car ride) in 1907. At a later period he writes about family activities and sailing. There are letters to his sister with occasional investment and banking advice, and his concern for the pending departure from the gold standard, noting in 1932 "it is anti-social to horde money at this stage."
  - Correspondence